all right
[Music]
the Harvard nurses health study women
who got five or fewer hours of sleep at
night gained about six pounds more over
the subsequent 16 years than those
getting seven a night even if that was
all due to the difference in sleep
that's still only six pounds for 10 000
plus more hours of sleep if even a tiny
fraction of that time was spent on diet
and exercise you know biking to the
nearest Farm Stand more weight could
have been lost in 16 weeks than in those
16 years every little bit helps though
and getting at least seven hours is
healthier for you anyway
the biggest reason to lose sleep over
losing sleep is motor vehicle accident
risk driving drowsy increases risk of
killing yourself and others people might
think twice about getting behind the
wheel after staying awake for 48 hours
straight but even just two weeks of
sleeping six hours a night impairs your
cognitive performance as much as pulling
two all-nighters in a row
so what's the best way to sleep better
sleeping pills are a non-starter those
prescribed even less than 18 pills a
year of so-called hypnotics the class of
sleeping pills that includes Ambien
appear to have triple the risk of dying
prematurely since up to 10 percent of
the adult population is prescribe these
drugs if the drugs really are killing
people that can mean a six-figure death
toll every year
Ambience manufacturer questioned the
study but that's just one of dozens of
studies that found a significant
association between sleeping pills and
premature death when the principal
investigator at the Scripps Clinic Sleep
Center was criticized for reporting
alarmingly High death risks from these
commonly used medications he replied we
can't hide risks even if they might
frighten patients out of taking
hypnotics patience have a right to know
what's more non-pharmacological methods
have been found to work as good or
better than the drugs the recommended
first line treatment for insomnia is
what's called cognitive behavioral
therapy which combines conditioning
techniques to reassociate the bed with
sleep and education surrounding optimal
sleep hygiene here are the four rules of
sleep conditioning number one go to bed
only when you're sleeping number two
only use the bed for sleep and sex no
reading eating or screen time number
three if you can't fall asleep within
about the 15-20 minutes get up leave the
bedroom and don't come back until you're
sleepy again and repeat as necessary and
finally number four get up at the same
time every morning no matter how little
sleep you get and although avoiding
napping is often added contrary to
expectations the majority of research
does not show that daytime naps
interfere with nighttime sleep if there
were four rules of sleep hygiene I'd
pick out it would be number one exercise
regularly the best time to exercise to
improve sleep appears to be four to
eight hours before bedtime though it
appears to be a myth that exercising
right before bed is somehow disruptive
to Sleep Number Two avoid caffeine
nicotine and alcohol before bedtime we
used to think as long as you don't drink
caffeine in the evening it wouldn't
affect sleep but four cups of coffee
worth even six hours before bedtime can
reduce Total Sleep Time by more than an
hour even just two cups in the morning
at seven a.m can change what your brain
waves look like on EEG that night though
it's not clear if this has any clinical
relevance Beyond delaying the onset of
sleep by an average of 10 minutes
late afternoon alcohol consumption six
hours before bedtime may also impair
sleep even after it's cleared out of
your system and nicotine whether from
gum pill patch or cigarette can also
have negative sleep effects though so
too can active nicotine withdrawal food
wise low fiber intakes and high
saturated fat and sugar intake is
associated with lighter less restorative
sleep meat intake is associated with
napping suggested as a proxy for
sleepiness this may be one of the
reasons insomnia has been reported as a
side effect of low carb ketogenic diets
supplement wise a single megadose of
vitamin D was found to improve sleep
duration and quality in men and women
ages 20 through 50 with sleeping
disorders and I've already talked about
melatonin-rich foods and supplements in
previous videos
number three make the bedroom quiet dark
cool and comfortable nocturnal noise can
adversely impact sleep even if we're not
consciously aware of it within a few
days you can become habituated to noises
such that they don't wake you up but EEG
studies and subjective sleep survey show
the quality of your sleep can still be
affected thankfully earplugs and sound
masking like white noise machines have
been shown to help and finally number
four establish a relaxing bedtime
routine relaxation techniques such as
massage mindfulness meditation and
soothing music may also help so may
taking a relaxing hot bath or shower one
of the reasons late night eating can
delay sleep is that it may interfere
with a drop in core body temperature
that normally occurs about bedtime
that's thought to be one of the cues
that it's time for bed so should you not
take a hot bath before bed no because as
soon as you step out of the bath or
shower the rapid decline and skin
temperature can accentuate the natural
nighttime drop and improve sleep even
just a warm foot bath may help you fall
asleep about 15 minutes faster
[Music]
thank you